<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[pyPipe3D]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>pyPipe3D</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 10:40:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 10:40:42 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Galactic chemical evolution - stellar yields and the initial mass function]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Models" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Models</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Galactic chemical evolution: stellar yields and the initial mass function"<br>
Year: 2015<br>
Authors: Mercedes Mollá, Oscar Cavichia, Marta Gavilán, Brad K. Gibson <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/galactic-chemical-evolution-stellar-yields-and-the-initial-mass-function.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Galactic chemical evolution - stellar yields and the initial mass function.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:21:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Influence of the Void Environment on Chemical Abundances in Dwarf Galaxies and Implications for Connecting Star Formation and Halo Mass]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Astrophysics" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Astrophysics</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Large_scale" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Large_scale</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Influence of the Void Environment on Chemical Abundances in Dwarf Galaxies and Implications for Connecting Star Formation and Halo Mass"<br>
Year: 2018<br>
Authors: Kelly A. Douglass, Michael S. Vogeley, Renyue Cen <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "In the relationship between N/O and O/H, all our dwarf galaxies reside on the so-called “nitrogen plateau,” where the N/O ratio is predicted to be independent of the gas-phase oxygen abundance for metallicities 12 + log(O/H) &lt; 8.5." (Page 19)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/influence-of-the-void-environment-on-chemical-abundances-in-dwarf-galaxies-and-implications-for-connecting-star-formation-and-halo-mass.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Influence of the Void Environment on Chemical Abundances in Dwarf Galaxies and Implications for Connecting Star Formation and Halo Mass.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:14:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Large-scale Environmental Dependence of the Abundance Ratio of Nitrogen to Oxygen in Blue, Star-forming Galaxies Fainter than L]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Large_scale" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Large_scale</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Large-scale Environmental Dependence of the Abundance Ratio of Nitrogen to Oxygen in Blue, Star-forming Galaxies Fainter than L&lt;sub&gt;*&lt;/sub&gt;"<br>
Year: 2017<br>
Authors: Kelly A. Douglass, Michael S. Vogeley <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "y looking at just N/O, we remove the hydrogen dependence of the relative abundances" (Page 2)<br> "Detecting a difference in the N/O ratio due to the large-scale environment would indicate that the cosmic environment has some influence on the nucleosynthesis of secondary element" (Page 2)<br> "In addition, if the environment does have some very minor effect on the metallicity of a galaxy, removing the hydrogen dependence could amplify this effect above the noise of the data." (Page 2)<br> "The signal-to-noise ratio of the SDSS spectra is too low to directly estimate the temperature of the gas in the low-ionization  zone." (Page 3)<br> "t" (Page 3)<br> "For nitrogen, we employ the ICFs as defined in Izotov et" (Page 3)<br> "y Pan et al." (Page 4)<br> "void dwarf galaxies have lower N/O" (Page 6)<br> "0.05±0.074" (Page 6)<br> "not statistically significan" (Page 6)<br> "The original shifts in the N/O ratio seen were still present after the downsampling; the observed shift in the N/O ratio is not due to any variations in the distribution of the stellar masses between the two environments." (Page 7)<br> "in galaxies. When the metallicity of a galaxy is low, stars created from this gas do not have enough carbon to efficiently produce helium via the CNO cycle. As a result, any nitrogen produced in these stars will behave as a primary element—it will be produced in the same relative quantity as oxygen. However, when the metallicity of a galaxy is high enough, stars are create" (Page 7)<br> "also find little or no evidence of a plateau in their study" (Page 8)<br> "−0.38±0.078" (Page 8)<br> "If a plateau in the O/H–N/O relation exists, then we should see a slope of 1 in the O/H–N/H relation. When looking at N/H as a function of O/H in Figure 10, we see that there is a correlation between the nitrogen and oxygen abundances." (Page 8)<br> "There is no difference between void and wall galaxies in the relationship of oxygen and nitrogen production in the lowmetallicity sample." (Page 9)<br> "tallicity in void dwarf galaxies than wall dwarf galaxies may be evidence of a difference in the ratio of dark matter halo mass to stellar mass between the two environments. Simulations by Jung et al. (2014) and Tonnesen &amp; Cen (2015) have shown that the dark matter halo masses of void central galaxies are larger than" (Page 12)<br>Not statistically significant. Even they say it (Page 12)<br> "Another explanation that would lead to a shift in the N/O ratio between environments" (Page 13)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/large-scale-environmental-dependence-of-the-abundance-ratio-of-nitrogen-to-oxygen-in-blue,-star-forming-galaxies-fainter-than-l.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Large-scale Environmental Dependence of the Abundance Ratio of Nitrogen to Oxygen in Blue, Star-forming Galaxies Fainter than L.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:14:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX"<br>
Year: 2007<br>
Authors: Ryan P. Mallery, Lisa Kewley, R. Michael Rich, Samir Salim, Stephane Charlot, Christy Tremonti, Mark Seibert, Todd Small, Ted Wyder, Tom A. Barlow, Karl Forster, Peter G. Friedman, D. Christopher Martin, Patrick Morrissey, Susan G. Neff, David Schiminovich, Luciana Bianchi, José Donas, Timothy M. Heckman, Young-Wook Lee, Barry F. Madore, Bruno Milliard, Alex S. Szalay, Barry Y. Welsh, Sukyoung Yi <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "temperatures to be overestimated, and that the strong-line abundances may be more correct, since their line ratios are not as temperature sensitive as [O iii] k436" (Page 485)<br> "McGaugh (1991)" (Page 485)<br> "For log (1⁄2N ii /H ) &gt; 1 and log (1⁄2N ii / 1⁄2O ii ) &gt; 0:8 we use the metal-rich expression. If 0:8&gt;log (1⁄2N ii / 1⁄2O ii ) &gt; 1:5" (Page 485)<br> "As galaxy" (Page 485)<br> "mass increases, T04 estimates an increasingly larger metallicity than the other two calibrations." (Page 486)<br> "t1⁄2N ii 1⁄4 0:6065 þ 0:1600x þ 0:1878x 2 þ 0:2803x 3; ð11Þ  where x log R23." (Page 486)<br>This expression is just N2O2 calibration (Page 486)<br> "og N þ  O þ 1⁄4 log 1⁄2N ii  1⁄2O ii  þ 0:307 0:02log t1⁄2N ii  0:726  t1⁄2N ii  ð12Þ" (Page 486)<br> "N/O 1⁄4 N þ /O þ. Thurston et al." (Page 486)<br> "because the FUV passband is responsive to star formation on timescales of 10 Myr and the NUV passband on timescales of 100 Myr" (Page 486)<br> "ogðN/OÞ 1⁄4 log 1⁄2a þ b ; ðO/ HÞ" (Page 487)<br>maybe use a fit like this (Page 487)<br> "We note that these three derivations for oxygen abundance are not completely independent of the nitrogen abundance. The O3N2 value depends on a flux ratio containing [ N ii] k6584, while R23 is used to calculate the [ N ii] temperature required to determine the N/O ratio" (Page 487)<br> "models used to derive T04 have prior distributions of metallicities, where nitrogen abundance is selected to have a only a primary dependence on the oxygen abundance below 12 þ log (O/H ) &lt; 8:25, and a completely secondary dependence for metallicities greater than this" (Page 487)<br>Ackwnoleged but not quantified? (Page 489)<br> "M91 calculation has the least dependence on the N/O diagnostic" (Page 489)<br> "the M91 and T04 diagnostics both indicate that for galaxies with similar O/H, the most extreme starbursts (highest values of SFR/M ) tend to have lower N/O." (Page 489)<br>the problem is that higher sSFR gives higher O/H in that bin and thus higher NO, not relevant (Page 489)<br> "n increments of 0.1 dex in log (O/ H )" (Page 489)<br> "x. As metallicity increases, and nitrogen becomes largely secondary in origin, and the difference between the N/O ratios of the subsample with the lowest specific star formation rates and the other two subsamples decreases." (Page 489)<br> "he O3N2 diagnostic shows the opposite trend of the other two diagnostics since O3N2 is not corrected for ionization parameter. At the lowest and highest metallicities no difference is found between the N/O ratios of the two subsamples in all three diagnostics" (Page 489)<br> "ervational constraints of the solar neighborhood. Galaxies with high specific star formation rates could also have galactic winds that differentially remove one element with respect to the other. With regards to differential flow of oxygen, van Zee &amp; Haynes (2006) examined the ratio of N/O for a sample of dwarf galaxies, and argued that their data suggests that either differential outflow of oxygen occurs in every galaxy in their sample with the" (Page 490)<br> "to the seven-band GALEX+SDSS" (Page 493)<br> "hotometry to indicate of the strength of the st" (Page 493)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/nitrogen-production-in-starburst-galaxies-detected-by-galex.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:14:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Oxygen and nitrogen abundances in Virgo and field spirals]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Large_scale" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Large_scale</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Oxygen and nitrogen abundances in Virgo and field spirals"<br>
Year: 2002<br>
Authors: L. S. Pilyugin, M. Mollá, F. Ferrini, J. M. Vílchez <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "It is well established that the spiral galaxies of the Virgo cluster have a tendency to be H i deficient in comparison with normal field spirals" (Page 14)<br> "and this deficiency is correlated with distance to the cluster center, the proportion of gas-poor spirals increasing continuously towards the cluster center" (Page 14)<br>ram pressure stripping (Page 14)<br> "i) the spirals at the periphery of the cluster are indistinguishable from the field galaxies, ii)" (Page 14)<br> "the H i deficient Virgo core galaxies have larger oxygen abundances at a predetermined galactocentric distance r = 0.4 R25" (Page 14)<br> "A new" (Page 15)<br> "way of oxygen abundance determination in H ii regions (P –method) has been recently suggested (Pilyugin 2000, 2001a)." (Page 15)<br> "it produces overestimated oxygen abundances in low-excitation H ii regions" (Page 15)<br> "The (O/H)P oxygen abundances in H ii regions are determined with the expression suggested in" (Page 15)<br> "P = R3/R23" (Page 15)<br> "range of luminosity" (Page 15)<br>Could be that mass efect is there as well (Page 15)<br> "morphological type" (Page 15)<br> "The oxygen abundances at r = 0.4 R25 have been used instead of the central oxygen abundances because the central oxygen abundances in these galaxies can be affected by large uncertainties:" (Page 16)<br> "There are no H i deficient Virgo spirals with low oxygen abundances." (Page 19)<br> "However, for H ii regions, in which the bulk of oxygen is in the O+ stage, the two values of t2 are not in agreement. Equations (1), (5)–(8) give a more realistic values of t2 for these H ii regions." (Page 20)<br> "or due to the uncertainty in the extrapolation of the P –method into an area of extreme values of the parameters P and R23" (Page 21)<br> "and the R23 value is usually less than 1 while the calibration is based on the H ii regions with R23 &gt; 2" (Page 21)<br> "ime scale τ0" (Page 22)<br> "collapse time scale and mass, it is evident that τcoll must be variable with the galactocentric radius. If the total mass surface density follows an exponential law, such as the surface brightness does for spiral disks, the resulting τcoll must increase along the radius with a scale length" (Page 22)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/oxygen-and-nitrogen-abundances-in-virgo-and-field-spirals.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Oxygen and nitrogen abundances in Virgo and field spirals.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:14:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[SDSS-IV MaNGA Variations in the NO-OH Relation Bias Metallicity Gradient Measurements]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "SDSS-IV MaNGA: Variations in the N/O–O/H Relation Bias Metallicity Gradient Measurements"<br>
Year: 2020<br>
Authors: Adam L. Schaefer, Christy Tremonti, Francesco Belfiore, Zachary Pace, Matthew A. Bershady, Brett H. Andrews, Niv Drory <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "Previous work has shown that in galaxies in the low-redshift universe, there are systematic radial variations in several of the quantities that can determine the N/O ratio at fixed O/H. Leroy et al. (2008) showed that the SFE (defined as the ratio between the star formation rate and the total molecular plus atomic gas mass) in spiral galaxies can vary by up to a factor of 10 between their centers and their outskirts, with the centers generally hosting more efficient star formation than at large radii" (Page 1)<br>Important effect: In our SDSS sample it could mean that galaxies with smaller apparent size could present sistematically be lower than those with larger (Page 1)<br> "Following Schaefer et al. (2019), we select only galaxies that are close to face-on by discarding galaxies with a minor to major axis ratio, b/a&lt;0.6. We further reject galaxies that have fewer than 60% of their observed spaxels in the star-forming region of the Baldwin et al. (1981) diagram." (Page 2)<br>Good practice (Page 2)<br> "The estimation of the N/O ratio suffers from smaller systematics than the estimation of O/H since the ionization potential of N+ and O+ are very similar (14.53 eV and 13.61 eV, respectively)." (Page 3)<br> "3. Results  With the measurements in place we are now in a position to explore the differences between our strong-line O/H indicators and the relationship between these differences and the relative abundance of nitrogen" (Page 3)<br>SFE differences affect N presence and Oxygen calibration with N included for the gradient (Page 3)<br> "We find that the Spearman rank correlation coefficient ranges  from ρ=−0.5 at 12 + log(O H) = 8.5 to ρ=−0.25 at  12 + log(O H) = 9.1" (Page 6)<br> "El-Badry et al. (2016) used high-resolution simulations to show that stars in a 1010.6 Me galaxy can migrate outward by ∼1–2 kpc within 1 Gyr of their formation" (Page 6)<br>Another N/O dispersion effect only in resolved galaxies (Page 6)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/sdss-iv-manga-variations-in-the-no-oh-relation-bias-metallicity-gradient-measurements.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/SDSS-IV MaNGA Variations in the NO-OH Relation Bias Metallicity Gradient Measurements.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:14:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Some caveats about the evolution of the NO abundance and the star formation history]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Astrophysics" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Astrophysics</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Astrophysics" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Astrophysics</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Models" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Models</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "Some caveats about the evolution of the N/O abundance and the star formation history"<br>
Year: 2010<br>
Authors: M. Molla, M. Gavilan <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/some-caveats-about-the-evolution-of-the-no-abundance-and-the-star-formation-history.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/Some caveats about the evolution of the NO abundance and the star formation history.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:21:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The competing effects of recent and long-term star formation histories on oxygen, nitrogen, and stellar metallicities]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Astrophysics" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Astrophysics</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "The competing effects of recent and long-term star formation histories on oxygen, nitrogen, and stellar metallicities"<br>
Year: 2025<br>
Authors: Nicholas Fraser Boardman, Vivienne Wild, Natalia Vale Asari, Francesco D'Eugenio <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "In weak potentials, galaxy SFR variations primarily result from recent gas inflows, mostly affecting gas abundances" (Page 1)<br> "In deeper potentials, SFR variations instead correspond to broad differences in SFH shapes resulting from differences in long-term gas consumption histories, which is most visible in stellar abundances." (Page 1)<br> "e.g. Lian et al. 2018; Fraser-McKelvie et al. 2022; Sa ́nchez-Menguiano et a" (Page 1)<br> "2024b; Stanton et al. 2024; Zhuang et al. 2024; Zinchenko &amp; Vı ́lchez 2024" (Page 1)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/the-competing-effects-of-recent-and-long-term-star-formation-histories-on-oxygen,-nitrogen,-and-stellar-metallicities.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/The competing effects of recent and long-term star formation histories on oxygen, nitrogen, and stellar metallicities.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 10:05:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Nitrogen-to-Oxygen evolution in galaxies - the role of the star formation rate]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Astrophysics" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Astrophysics</a> <a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "The Nitrogen-to-Oxygen evolution in galaxies: the role of the star formation rate"<br>
Year: 2006<br>
Authors: M. Mollá, J. M. Vílchez, M. Gavilán, A. I. Díaz <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/the-nitrogen-to-oxygen-evolution-in-galaxies-the-role-of-the-star-formation-rate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/The Nitrogen-to-Oxygen evolution in galaxies - the role of the star formation rate.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:21:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[THE STAR FORMATION HISTORY AND CHEMICAL EVOLUTION OF STAR-FORMING GALAXIES IN THE NEARBY UNIVERSE]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:Nitrogen" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#Nitrogen</a> 
 <br><br>Title: "THE STAR FORMATION HISTORY AND CHEMICAL EVOLUTION OF STAR-FORMING GALAXIES IN THE NEARBY UNIVERSE"<br>
Year: 2012<br>
Authors: J. P. Torres-Papaqui, R. Coziol, R. A. Ortega-Minakata, D. M. Neri-Larios <br><br>Related:: <br><br><br>
Write notes here!<br><br><br> "SFGs. For the metallicity, O/H, we used the method described in Vacca &amp; Conti (1992), which yields values with a typical uncertainty of the order of ±0.2 dex (Edmunds &amp; Pagel 1984)." (Page 5)<br>Theyre using R23 (Page 5)<br>]]></description><link>biblio-notes/the-star-formation-history-and-chemical-evolution-of-star-forming-galaxies-in-the-nearby-universe.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">biblio-notes/THE STAR FORMATION HISTORY AND CHEMICAL EVOLUTION OF STAR-FORMING GALAXIES IN THE NEARBY UNIVERSE.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 08:22:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Changes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Moved spectra to rest frame to ensure that the templates are well cropped. Adjust the number of components depending on the covered range of wv]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/ppxf/changes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pPXF/Changes.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 11:02:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mass-weighted]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>pPXF provides directly mass SFHs in  sps_util.  The process is the following:<br>Move flux units  from the flux band (without 1+z correction, should add this), , where  is each template. To 10 pc and use solar luminosity units<br>
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/ppxf/mass-weighted.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pPXF/Mass-weighted.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 13:59:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Montecarlo bootstrapping]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The goal is to calculate uncertainties on the SFH to check whether they are compatible with the ones derived with pyPipe4U]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/ppxf/montecarlo-bootstrapping.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pPXF/Montecarlo bootstrapping.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 13:58:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Doubts]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>0.43 in the error calculation comes from log10(e), but why applied to the extinction error?
<br>Why that formula for the extinction error? 
<br>What is the correct way to estimate error calculation in the MC SFH iteration?
<br>How should maStar models be used? sigma_inst=0 and no other fix?
<br>Why values of EL fitting are negative sometimes? Should they? Because We are using LM method, least square fitting should be bounded either way, but who knows
<br>How should SFH be correlated? should there be any correlation between T30 and T70??
<br>==How come the error in the EL does not depend on the number of pixels in the fitting? Particularly in the continuum<br>
This is from the formula  where  and  is the standard deviation of the residuals for gas-only spectrum  
<br>The program does not ignore very large error values, it fits its either way
<br>There is a latter search of parameters for SSPs for some reason, what are the implications of this
<br>Investigate: Why 3500 factor in mass. This is not used in pyPipe3D
<br>Why only half the sigma noise is used in the gaussian fit? 0.5 for the randomize_flux option
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pyfit3d/doubts.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pyFIT3D/Doubts.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 10:00:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Ca K line is not well fitted, looks like it is because there is a sky line just there.<br>
There are some galaxies such as 12935 that have an emission line between Hgamma and H9. It is the Ne III 3868 line (low metal?) <br>
<br>Whenever the EL fit fails is because the EL is outside of the boundaries defined in autossp, this is commonly because the redshift is ill-determined
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pyfit3d/notes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pyFIT3D/Notes.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 11:32:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[To implement]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Uncertainties calculation on mass<br>
Solve both the emission infinite and outside of range]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pyfit3d/to-implement.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pyFIT3D/To implement.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 11:21:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Configuring ini file]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The most important parameters are:<br>
<br> Estimates for the center of the galaxxy
<br>redshift, to guide the search and speed up the process
<br>badpix_extension=3 for CAVITY
<br>badpix_value=1 (bad pixel value)
<br>instrumental_dispersion = 2.31 (2.51 A for gsd, 6 for CAVITY PPak)<br>
This info is in <a data-href="File headers" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/file-headers.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">File headers</a> and <a data-href="Instrument parameters" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/instrument-parameters.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Instrument parameters</a>
<br>Segmentation options: whatever you like]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/configuring-ini-file.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/CAVITY IFU/Configuring ini file.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:34:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[File headers]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="header.png" src="lib/media/header.png"><br>Error weighting factor is related to the reliability of the result given the fiber coverage. Should only affect averages (I believe)]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/file-headers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/CAVITY IFU/File headers.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 09:12:17 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib/media/header.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib/media/header.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Instrument parameters]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Wavelength coverage: <br>
with linear spacing and   for the whole range<br>
Instrumental resolution FWHM:  for whole range of wavelength<br>
<img alt="wavelength_info.png" src="lib/media/wavelength_info.png"><br>This means:<br>
<br>No resampling
<br>No degrading spectra. Fixed difference (if models have 2.51 this means ~ 2.31 A )
<br>Technically should consider changes with redshift
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/instrument-parameters.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/CAVITY IFU/Instrument parameters.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:57:11 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib/media/wavelength_info.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib/media/wavelength_info.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[README]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>This vault contains all information regarding the data processing and information for CAVITY DR1, which I need for pyPipe3D's pipeline<br>
<br><a data-href="File headers" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/file-headers.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">File headers</a>
<br><a data-href="Instrument parameters" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/instrument-parameters.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Instrument parameters</a>
<br><a data-href="Configuring ini file" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/configuring-ini-file.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Configuring ini file</a>
<br>Some annotations for myself:<br>
<br><a data-href="TODO" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/todo.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">TODO</a>
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/readme.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/CAVITY IFU/README.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:39:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[TODO]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Parametric emission line fit is not working. This is most probably because of the same issue of having a wavelength range not corrected for redshift in the range that I had for SDSS. 
<br>Change the dispersion. Not only general but in RSS analysis. Should we take into account the redshift correction?
<br>Implement foreground extinction correction NOO, it is already done in the cubes
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/cavity-ifu/todo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/CAVITY IFU/TODO.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 08:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Central Spectrum Analysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The central spectrum analysis is performed<br>In the example CALIFA code this means:<br>If no center is defined, a weighted estimate is calculated as the flux^5 average in the V slice within<br>
the center third of the cube.<br>
# If no center pixel is given
if x0 is None or y0 is None:
	nx0 = int(nx*.33)
	nx1 = int(nx*2*.33) # 1/3 central part
	ny0 = int(ny*.33)
	ny1 = int(ny*2*.33)
	iy, ix = np.indices(V__yx.shape)
	iy = iy[ny0:ny1, nx0:nx1]
	ix = ix[ny0:ny1, nx0:nx1]
	sel = V_msk__yx[ny0:ny1, nx0:nx1] != 2
	V_slice = copy(V__yx[ny0:ny1, nx0:nx1][sel])
	__V = V_slice**5
	_s = __V.sum()
	x0 = ix[sel].dot(__V)/_s # Mean position for ^5 weighted average
	y0 = iy[sel].dot(__V)/_s
<br>Then radial_sum_cube_e is called, calculating the cube that will be used for the analysis, it returns the central spectrum in the output[0] and integrated spectrum in the output[5] position. This analysis is not tessellated yet.<br>A first round off nonlinear fit is performed, then an emission lines one in the central integrated spaxel.<br>Then, a full-galaxy integrated spectrum analysis is performed<br>These two would give the redshift if it was not fixed in the ini file.]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/central-spectrum-analysis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Steps/Central Spectrum Analysis.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 08:07:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Continuum Segmentation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Continuum segmentation consists in two steps:<br>
<br>Join pixels with close values of integrated flux in the V-pseudoband 
<br>Voronoi binning to achieve a given S/N (around 50 usually)
<br>In the CALIFA pipeline this means:<br># Step to obtain the segmented spectra
cont_seg_all_SN()


# Extract statistics from segmented spectra
rss_mean, _, _, _, _  = spec_extract_cube_mean()
rss_error, _, _, _, _ = spec_extract_cube_error()
get_SN_rss()
SN_map_seg()
rss_seg2cube()

# Get V-band slice
get_slice()

# True analysis. This function just for loops for every spectum
r = auto_ssp_elines_rnd_rss_main(wave, rss_mean, rss_error)
# The result is stored in rss.few
# Returns an emission-free spectrum per spaxel that is passed down again
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/continuum-segmentation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Steps/Continuum Segmentation.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:50:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Emission line fit for spaxel]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>A rescaled (flux) and dezonificated stellar population model constructed for the tesella corresponding to the spaxel is used to obtain a pure gas spectre. A polynomial correction is applied to remove the possible color effects (non specified in the paper).<br>Both a parametric (gaussian) and non-parametric fit is done.<br>For the parametric fit, the following code is executed:<br>r = kin_cube_elines_main()
<br>This performs parametric (gaussian + continuum) fit for every spaxel and file of models given.<br>For the momentum analysis (just measuring std and integrated flux)<br>r = flux_elines_cube_EW()
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/emission-line-fit-for-spaxel.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Steps/Emission line fit for spaxel.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 08:07:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Final calculations]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Generates mass, age, and metallicity maps:<br>sum_mass_age(...)
<br>where the function calculates the mass  with:<br>
<br>
where  is the flux for a given stellar  stellar population in the pixel  and  the corresponding coefficient for the given SSP and fit. And corrects it with the redshift multiplying by a luminosity factor depending on the cosmological model and luminosity distance.<br>The error comes directly from the error in :<br>
<br>
The dust correction is directly:<br>
<br>
in the code they use  for some reason]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/final-calculations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Steps/Final calculations.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 09:15:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Tesella fit]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Each tesella is analysed with a parametric emission line fit and SSP.:<br>r = auto_ssp_elines_rnd_rss_main(...)
<br>The results for the full spectral fitting are saved in auto_ssp.CS_few.NAME.rss.out<br>
Then, a SSP only fit is done with the non-linear parameters obtained from the whole fit (sigma_star, Av, redshift) and fixed (much faster). The results are saved in auto_ssp.CS.NAME.rss.out<br>Then a GAS cube is obtained which will be used for the emission line fit ]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/tesella-fit.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Steps/Tesella fit.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 09:45:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Doubts]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Why does the instrumental dispersion change between the different steps in the whole procedure? e.g, the first round and second round of RSS
<br>Why do a masked and unmasked analysis of the central spectrum?
<br>What to do with extremely large (bad fitting) values for EL fitting?
<br>Any changes in the pipeline?
<br>The redshift should be taken into account for the sigma dispersion. Is it done? Probably not.  See Cappellari 2017 MNRAS 466, 798–811
<br>There are no uncertainties in the dust-corrected stellar mass?
<br> Are flux in flux_elines rescaled to something? 
<br>]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/doubts.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/Doubts.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 09:18:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[PyPipe3D map]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>This vault  will contain all the information necessary to understand <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08027" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2202.08027" target="_blank">PyPipe3D</a> in a simple straightforward manner<br>
This includes <a data-href="The pipeline" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/the-pipeline.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">The pipeline</a>]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/pypipe3d-map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/PyPipe3D map.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 07:32:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[pypipe4u for sebas]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Changes made in pypipe4u that should be taken into account either in the LVM DAP or pyPipe3D<br>FOR LVM:<br>The masked emission lines are ill-selected, best to ignore either in the sum or altogether<br>
The error is not properly calculated. The mean is used, but the result is a broad band (squared mean)]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/pypipe4u-for-sebas.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/pypipe4u for sebas.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 10:01:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The pipeline]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The pipeline consists in the following steps:<br>
<br><a data-href="Central Spectrum Analysis" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/central-spectrum-analysis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Central Spectrum Analysis</a>
<br><a data-href="Continuum Segmentation" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/continuum-segmentation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Continuum Segmentation</a>
<br><a data-href="Execute Nonlinear, emission and SSP fit for each tessela" href="Execute Nonlinear, emission and SSP fit for each tessela" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Execute Nonlinear, emission and SSP fit for each tessela</a>
<br>Stellar indices analysis
<br><a data-href="Emission line fit for spaxel" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/emission-line-fit-for-spaxel.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Emission line fit for spaxel</a> 
<br><a data-href="Final calculations" href="full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/steps/final-calculations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Final calculations</a>
]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe3d/the-pipeline.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/PyPipe3D/The pipeline.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 10:26:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[pyPipe4U]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The repository and documentation can be found in:<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://gitlab.com/yllari/py-pipe-4-u" target="_blank">https://gitlab.com/yllari/py-pipe-4-u</a><br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://yllari.gitlab.io/py-pipe-4-u/" target="_blank">https://yllari.gitlab.io/py-pipe-4-u/</a><br>
respectively.]]></description><link>full-spectral-fitting/pypipe4u.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Full spectral fitting/pyPipe4U.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 13:50:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1. Delayed nitrogen production]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/1.-delayed-nitrogen-production.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/1. Delayed nitrogen production.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 14:39:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2. About SFHs]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>WIP]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/2.-about-sfhs.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/2. About SFHs.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 08:15:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[3. Large scale structure effects]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>To carry out the analysis of Large scale structure effects we use Dominguez-Gómez's sample with the following filters:<br>
<br>Median  &gt; 10
<br>Star-forming galaxy from diagnostic NII-OIII Kauffman diagram
<br>
<br>Petrosian radius 90 &lt; 20 (Dominguez filter, maybe not necessary, but we should control for the<br>
radial O/H and Nitrogen gradient at some point)
<br> in all emission lines used for calibration (either N/O or O/H)<br>
These filters result in a sample with: 593, 826, and 855 galaxies for clusters, filaments,  and  voids with good N/O values.
<br>For this text, I will be using R23-P calibrator from Pilyugin 2001, which constraints the number of galaxies to CLUSTERS: 298, FILAMENTS: 562, VOIDS: 611 (A&amp;A 369, 594–604),<br>
by forcing correct S/N on all necessary lines. I also used the O3N2 and N2 calibrations from Merino+2013, the R23-O23 calibration from Kobulnicky+1999 (analytical expression from the numerical McGaugh+1991) and R23 Tremonti's derived and calibrated O/H. All of these are not shown<br><br>The color-mass distribution is very similar. No mass control will be applied for now.<br>
<img alt="g-r LSS.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/g-r-lss.png"><br>The O/H -N/O distribution (go to Imgs/OH_NO LSS to see it bigger or click if the plugin is activated)  <br><img alt="OH_NO LSS.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/oh_no-lss.png"><br>
The only significant by-eye difference is in the redshift range, as expected because of the CAVITY selection criteria, and some cluster galaxies with low N/O in the high-O/H end. Is this a real thing or an artifact? Under our current paradigm this would mean that cluster galaxies have surprisingly high star formation activities when compared to either filaments or voids.<br>The difference is there when we bin in O/H and plot the mean an std values (as in the following Fig., where the running mean for each environment is also plotted as a continuous line and the colors are the same as in the previous Fig.). BUT, difficult to asses whether this is statistically significant or not.<br>
<img alt="LSS-median.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/lss-median.png"><br><br>To test the hypothesis that there is a secondary dependence of sSFR for the O/H-N/O relation, we bin in O/H and fit a linear relation O/H-N/O inside. This linear model is substracted to the data in order to obtain some residuals. Finally, the residuals are fitted with the sSFR.  This is not a good parametrization, just a simple test<br>CAVEATS: It could be the case that since whatever we use as a proxy for sSFR (either from MPA, g-r, or fom full spectral fitting) will be correlated with mass, we are only determining the oxygen with<br>
greater precision by adding a secondary parameter. This has to be tested in order to use this exercise as an argument. In the same manner, it could be the case that the calibrator used for the oxygen is sensible to SFR. In that case we run into the exact same problem as before.<br>
Also, R23 is double-valued, and we could be breaking said degeneracy with our secondary parameter.<br>As the sSFR indicator, we will be using the color  provided by SDSS (MPA?), which is highly correlated with the sSFR derived from MPA SFR and log(Mstar):<br>
<img alt="corr_gr_sSFR.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/corr_gr_ssfr.png"><br>For our oxygen calibrator and cluster galaxies, the result for this fitting is shown in blue in the following (left) Fig, as well as the first linear model and the data (in red). ignoring the first two bins, denoted by the vertical blue lines, we see that much of the dispersion in the N/O plane can be characterized with the secondary sSFR parameter.<br>
This can also be seen in the right Fig. with the Pearson correlation coefficient, , per bin, which is  for all bins (ignoring the first two).<br><img alt="fit_R23.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/fit_r23.png"><img alt="corr_R23.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/corr_r23.png"><br>By contrast, when we employ the O3N2 calibrator, the fit is much worse and the correlation coefficients remain low .<br><img alt="OH_NO_model_cluster.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/oh_no_model_cluster.png"> <img alt="corr_O3N2.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/corr_o3n2.png">]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/3.-large-scale-structure-effects.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/3. Large scale structure effects.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 14:00:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/g-r-lss.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/g-r-lss.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[4. Large scale structure effects revisited. Parametric fit]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>To carry out the analysis of Large scale structure effects we use Dominguez-Gómez's sample with the following filters:<br>
<br>Median  &gt; 10
<br>Star-forming galaxy from diagnostic NII-OIII Kauffman diagram
<br>
<br>Petrosian radius 90 &lt; 20 (Dominguez filter, maybe not necessary, but we should control for the<br>
radial O/H and Nitrogen gradient at some point)
<br> in all emission lines used for calibration (either N/O or O/H)
<br>The Oxygen calibrator used is McGaugh1991+ R23 with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="[Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX" data-href="[Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX" href="[Nitrogen Production in Starburst Galaxies Detected by GALEX" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Mallery2007+</a><br>
These filters result in a number of galaxies (filaments analysed sample is about a third of all 15000 galaxies):<br>
CLUSTERS   FILAMENTS   VOIDS<br>
315                744                  605<br><br>CAVEATS: It could be the case that since whatever we use as a proxy for sSFR (either from MPA, g-r, or fom full spectral fitting) will be correlated with mass, we are only determining the oxygen with<br>
greater precision by adding a secondary parameter. This has to be tested in order to use this exercise as an argument. In the same manner, it could be the case that the calibrator used for the oxygen is sensible to SFR. In that case we run into the exact same problem as before. Also, R23 is double-valued, and we could be breaking said degeneracy with our secondary parameter.<br>As opposed to <a data-href="3. Large scale structure effects" href="n_o-comparison/3.-large-scale-structure-effects.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">3. Large scale structure effects</a>, we simplify the process by creating a single O/H-N/O parametrization of the form:<br><br>where . This is an adapted expression from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="SDSS-IV MaNGA Variations in the NO-OH Relation Bias Metallicity Gradient Measurements" data-href="SDSS-IV MaNGA Variations in the NO-OH Relation Bias Metallicity Gradient Measurements" href="biblio-notes/sdss-iv-manga-variations-in-the-no-oh-relation-bias-metallicity-gradient-measurements.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Schaefer2020+</a>, but with a reescaling factor, , to encompass any calibration. This fit is carried out with all galaxies (1664)<br>
<img alt="parametrization_OH_NO.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/parametrization_oh_no.png"><br>The resulting fit is:<br><br>We can define the excess of nitrogen, , as the difference between the observed N/O and the the fitted relation.<br>
<img alt="excess_no.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/excess_no.png"><br>By binning in oxgen, we can (partly) avoid sSFR-OH effects. Here the results discussed for different parameters. The fitting correspond to an ODR fitting (although the only data from MPA with errorbars was the stellar mass)<br>
Mass from MPA:<br>
<img alt="All_mass.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/all_mass.png"><br>Color (g-r) from MPA<br>
<img alt="All_gr.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/all_gr.png"><br>sSFR from MPA<br>
<img alt="All_ssfr_MPA.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/all_ssfr_mpa.png"><br>sSFR from pyPipe3D Integrated up to 100 Myr <br><img alt="All_ssfr_pypipe.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/all_ssfr_pypipe.png"><br>
The spearman coefficient and the slopes of the fits to the excess nitrogen, , show that the correlation is larger in the first bin and decreases with increasing oxygen. One possible explanation could be that the dispersion that can be explained physically (sSFR lower N/O) decreases relative to the the intrinsic observational scatter. The correlation would be lower, because the "signal to noise ratio" decreases. This can easily be illustrated if we consider both of them increasing the variance as . As the absolute variance caused by the sSFR increases, the predicting capability of the sSFR on the variance decreases.<br><br>There are no large differences between large-scale environments, since the overall sSFR distribution is the same (only the mass formed and the present mass being formed are the primary variables).<br>
To check this, we fix  as the parameter and show, from first to last: voids, clusters and filaments.<br>Voids<br>
<img alt="voids_gr.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/voids_gr.png"><br>
Clusters<br>
<img alt="Clusters_gr.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/clusters_gr.png"><br><img alt="Filaments_gr.png" src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/filaments_gr.png">]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/4.-large-scale-structure-effects-revisited.-parametric-fit.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/4. Large scale structure effects revisited. Parametric fit.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 09:50:15 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/parametrization_oh_no.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/parametrization_oh_no.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Current concept map]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 Fundamental N/O - O/H relationTESTS: AGN activity mass-controlledTESTS: AGN activity oxygen-controlledLarge scale structureOverall NO-OH ideasExcess N/OCalibrators<br>AGN activity and shock ionization:<br>
<br>We divide all galaxies into two samples depending wheter g-r&gt; median(g-r) and viceversa.
<br>We force them to have the same logMass distribution
<br>We apply the KS test to the N/O excess distributions
<br>We apply the KS test to the SII/Halpha distributions
<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/mass_controlled_agn.png" draggable="false">mass_controlled_AGN.png<br>Mallery2007+ analysis uses O3N2 and Tremonti+2004 and still finds differences, problem in analysis since no primary O/H-N/O relation is taken into account<br>R23 seems to be the most robust calibrator for independent oxygen values, used in SIGNALS (Bresolin+ 2025). To separate, they kind of use N/O ratios to make sure that the oxygen is above certain threshold. Some concerns: there could be sSFR dependence on the calibrator (maybe it is addressed by O23, because it correlates with ionization, but who knows). Two typical calibrations -&gt; R23-P (Pilyugin) and R23-O23, related. <br>Currently we use: R23, R23-P, O3N2, N2<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/mass_controlled_agn_no.png" draggable="false">mass_controlled_AGN_NO.png<br>In the N/O-O/H space<br>In the N/O excess dist. KS=1.76e-6<br>What is the best parameter to adjust for this secondary dependence? The usual division is decreasing or increasing SFR, but that can be summarised in two params: <br>
<br>The cumulated past SFR (Stellar mass)
<br>The integrated SFR up to the time delay between massive and LIM death stars: this can be empirically constrained by trying out different timescales and look for the highest correlation.
<br>Douglass+2021 finds only small efect in the O/H-N/O distribution for dwarf galaxies (O/H &lt; 8.5) by comparing void and field galaxies (in the plateau). Uses direct method <br>Pilyugin2002+ finds a lower N/O ratio for high Oxygen cluster (Virgo) galaxies but disregards it as statistical effects. Uses R23-P<br>Contini2002+ finds similar trend in Coma and Abell 1367 clusters, but advises some caution because the extinction could be underestimated. The given explanation is that their UV-selected galaxies are specially starburst. R23-O23  from McGaugh+1991, Kobulnicky+1999 is used<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/mass_controlled_agn_sii.png" draggable="false">mass_controlled_AGN_sii.png<br>In the SII/Halpha dist. KS=0.44<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/douglass2021+.png" draggable="false">Douglass2021+.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/contini2002+.png" draggable="false">Contini2002+.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/pilyugin2002+.png" draggable="false">Pilyugin2002+.png<br>Boardmann+2025 proposes two major ways that the O/H-N/O-SFH relation is affected by SFH depending on the potential: small potentials with recent changes in SFH, large potentials with great differences  in overall SFH. Also, of course, everything in between.<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/boardmann_diagram.png" draggable="false">boardmann_diagram.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/boardmann_fnr.png" draggable="false">boardmann_FNR.png<br>Mass, potential vs N/O<br>AGN activity and shock ionization:<br>
<br>We divide all galaxies into two samples depending wheter g-r&gt; median(g-r) and viceversa.
<br>We force them to have the same Oxygen distribution
<br>We apply the KS test to the N/O excess distributions
<br>We apply the KS test to the SII/Halpha distributions
<br>In the N/O excess dist. KS=2e-48<br>In the N/O-O/H space<br>In the SII/Halpha dist. KS=4.68e-6<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/oh_controlled_agn.png" draggable="false">oh_controlled_AGN.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/oh_controlled_agn_no.png" draggable="false">oh_controlled_AGN_NO.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/oh_controlled_agn_sii.png" draggable="false">oh_controlled_AGN_sii.png<br>We define the excess N/O as the distance to the parametric O/H-N/O fit<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/parametrization_oh_no.png" draggable="false">parametrization_OH_NO.png<img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/excess_no.png" draggable="false">excess_no.png<br><a data-href="1. Delayed nitrogen production" href="n_o-comparison/1.-delayed-nitrogen-production.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1. Delayed nitrogen production</a> is responsible for the relation between SFH and differences in N/O at same O/H<br>The Mass-SFR relation never really allow us to eliminate the effect of mass on our sSFR -&gt; distance to FMR as the new "sSFR indicator". WIP]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/current-concept-map.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/Current concept map.canvas</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 10:36:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/mass_controlled_agn.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="n_o-comparison/assets/imgs/mass_controlled_agn.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Important References]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Bibliography:<br><br>Only large-scale:<br><br>Only nitrogen-oxygen analysis<br>]]></description><link>n_o-comparison/important-references.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">N_O comparison/Important References.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 10:05:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[biblio-notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Title: "{{title | escape}}"<br>
Year: {{date | format("YYYY")}}<br>
Authors: {{authors}} <br><br>Related:: {% for relation in relations | selectattr("citekey") %} <a data-href="{{relation.citekey}}" href="{{relation.citekey}}" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">{{relation.citekey}}</a>{% if not loop.last %}, {% endif%} {% endfor %}<br><br>{% persist "notes" %}{% if isFirstImport %}<br>
Write notes here!<br>
{% endif %}<br>
{% endpersist %}<br><br>{% for annotation in annotations -%}<br>
{%- if annotation.annotatedText -%}<br>
{% if annotation.color %} "{{annotation.annotatedText | safe}}" {% else %} {{annotation.type | capitalize}} {% endif %}(Page {{annotation.pageLabel}})<br>
{%- endif %}<br>
{% if annotation.comment %}<br>
{{annotation.comment | safe}} (Page {{annotation.pageLabel}})<br>
{% endif %}<br>
{%- if annotation.imageRelativePath %}<br>
“” could not be found.<br>
{%- endif %}<br>
{% if annotation.allTags %}<br>
{{annotation.allTags}}<br>
{% endif %}<br>
{% endfor -%}]]></description><link>templates/biblio-notes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">templates/biblio-notes.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 16:12:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to navigate]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The latest information regarding pyPipe3D and the N/O relation exploration will be uploaded and updated here. One can find the main progress in N_O comparison.<br>pyPipe4U links:<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://gitlab.com/yllari/py-pipe-4-u" target="_blank">https://gitlab.com/yllari/py-pipe-4-u</a><br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://yllari.gitlab.io/py-pipe-4-u/" target="_blank">https://yllari.gitlab.io/py-pipe-4-u/</a>]]></description><link>how-to-navigate.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">How to navigate.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 13:50:48 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>